{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This country purged its military in the 2000s on the basis of the “Ergenekon” [[ar-geh-NEH-kon]] ultra-nationalist conspiracy. In 2019, this country launched Operation Peace Spring after the U.S. pulled its support from Kurdish allies. This country has been accused of democratic backsliding and IslamismundertheAKP,orJusticeandDevelopment Party, hurting theirchancesofjoiningtheEU.Fortenpoints,namethiscountryledbyRecep Tayyip Erdoğan [[reh-CHEP ty-EEP EHR-duh-wahn]].",
      "answer": "Republic ofTurkeyorTürkiyeCumhuriyeti"
    },
    {
      "question": "In an early experimental version of this literary form, Lawrence Sterne used a page of black ink to illustrate sorrow. This form's \"sentimental\" genre is exemplified by Samuel Richardson's 1740 work, Pamela; or Virtue Rewarded. This form separated from the traditional romance during the early eighteenth century with the publication of Moll Flanders and Robinson Crusoe by Daniel Defoe. For ten points, name this lengthy form of narrative writing, typified by Jonathan Swift'sGulliver'sTravels. ANSWER:Novel(acceptNovella; accept SentimentalNovel; accept TravelNovel; prompt on \"romance\" before mentioned; prompt on answers such as \"book\") (3) Vietnam veteran Kenneth Deardorff is the last man to make use of this act, facilitating his move to Alaska to open a generalstorealongtheStonyRiver.HoraceGreeley and George Henry Evans were early advocates of this law, with the latter running on the platform of \"Vote Yourself aFarm.\"TheKinkaidActamendedthislaw,allowinglargeswaths oflandtobeclaimedinthedepopulatedregionoftheSandhillsinwesternNebraska.Forten points, name this 1862 act that allowed Americans to claim public land for free as long as they farmed it. ANSWER:HomesteadAct of 1862 (acceptHomesteadAct[s]) (4) While serving as Secretary of State under this president, John Clayton negotiated a treaty with Henry Bulwer of the U.K. concerning spheres of influence in Central America. This man’s daughter,Sarah,marriedJeffersonDaviswhoservedunderthismanattheBattle of Buena Vista [[BWEH-nah VEES-tah]]. This Whig defeated Lewis Cass and Martin van Buren in the 1848 U.S. presidential election. For ten points, name this Mexican-American War hero who succeeded James K. Polk as president of the United States.",
      "answer": "ZacharyTaylor 2021-22 C Set History"
    },
    {
      "question": "During the Bellingham Riots in Washington, over 100 people of this faith were placed into \"protective custody\" by the Asiatic Exclusion League. This faith names an \"Empire\" which formed when various misl [[MEE-suhl]] states united to take advantage of the rapidly deteriorating Mughal [[moo-GAHL]] Empire. Bodyguards of this faith assassinated Indira[[in-DIH-ruh]]GandhifollowingviolenceinthePunjabduringOperation Blue Star. Gobind Singh [[goh-BIHND \"SING\"]] and Guru Nanak led, for ten points, which minority faith of India? ANSWER:Sikhism (orSikhi; acceptSikhs) (6) This one-time stateattorneygeneralarguedinfavorofthedefendantinthecaseVan Ordern v. Perry which concerned a Ten CommandmentsmonumentsattheStateHouse.The Anti-Defamation League censured this politician for comparing mass shootings to the Holocaust after the Sutherland Springs tragedy. This man provoked criticism when he blamed the unimplemented \"Green New Deal\" for his state's power plant failure during a 2021 ice storm. The Texas Heartbeat Act was signed by, for ten points, which Republican governor?",
      "answer": "GregAbbottor Gregory WayneAbbott"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man transformed the Italian cruiser Ramb III into his own personal yacht, Galeb. With the monarchist Chetniks, this man's forces resisted the Axis collaborationist government, including the Croatian Ustashe [[ooh-STAH-shuh]]. The Informbiro [[in-form-BEE-roh]] Period occurred after this communist leadersplitwithJosefStalin,and this man was later one of the founders of the \"Non-Aligned Movement.\" A united socialist Yugoslavia was led by, for ten points, which commander of the Partisans?",
      "answer": [
        "JosipBrozTito",
        "either underlinedportion",
        "MarshalTito"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man created a \"Spirit Thermometer\" filled with liquor to be displayed in the courtofhispatron,FerdinandoIIdeMedici.PopeUrbanVIII's[[theeighth's]]inquisitorsled an investigation against this man after he published “Dialogue Concerning the Two Chief World Systems.” A legends tells how this man dropped two balls of different massesoffthe Leaning Tower to test an Aristotelian hypothesis. Four moons of Jupiter are named for, for ten points, which Italian physicist and astronomer? ANSWER:GalileoGalilei(orGalileodi Vincenzo Bonaiutide'Galilei; accept either underlined portion) 2021-22 C Set History (9) Following his return from exile, this monarch formally abandoned the institutionof slavery in 1942 in an effort to finish the reforms of Yohannes IV.Thisman,whobannedthe Oromo language, was removed by the communist Derg regime. This negus [[NEH-gus]] failed to resist an Italian invasion in the 1930s, leading to his nation'soccupation.Thefinal emperor of Ethiopia was, for ten points, what monarch, sometimes known asRasTafari?",
      "answer": [
        "HaileSelassieI",
        "RasTafaribefore mentioned",
        "LijTafari Makonnen before \"Tafari\"",
        "Lij Tafari before \"Tafari\"",
        "Lij TafariMakonnen"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This nation's prime minister-in-exile gave the \"Comments on the Instructions” speech, instructing public servants to resist the orders of its Reichskommissariat [[RIKES-kohm-ee-SAHR-yaht]]. Operation Market Garden aimed to liberate this nation by capturing bridgeheads across the Rhine. During the Holocaust, diarist Anne Frank and her family lived in the \"Secret Annex\" in the capital city of, for ten points, what European nation?",
      "answer": [
        "Kingdom of theNetherlandsor KoninkrijkderNederlanden",
        "acceptHolland 2021-22 C Set History"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man is depicted with an adult's head and a child's body clutching an axe in a Grant Wood painting whose title figure opens a red curtain. DuringtheWarof1812,Dolley MadisonorderedherslavestorecovertheLansdowneportraitofthisman.Apaintingofthis man leading troops on a boat anachronistically contains an American flag. For ten points, name this U.S. president, who was depicted by Emanuel Leutze [[LOYT-zuh] Crossing the Delaware.",
        "answer": "GeorgeWashington"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This other U.S. president was depicted with a hand on a pillar in a RalphE.W.Earl painting. This promoter of the \"spoils system\" was depicted as a king holding a veto and trampling on the U.S. Constitution in a political cartoon railing against his triumph in the Bank War.",
        "answer": "AndrewJackson"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A major figure in this movement defined it in an essay titled \"Answering the Question: What is [this movement]?\" This movement's idealsweresupposedlyespousedby monarchs like Catherine the Great and were often spread through meetings at Masonic Lodges, coffeehouses, and salons. Preceded by Renaissance Humanism and the Scientific Revolution, for ten points, what intellectual movement of the 17th and 18th centuries was espoused by figures such as Immanuel Kant [[KAHNT]] and Voltaire?",
        "answer": [
          "Age ofEnlightenment",
          "Age ofReason",
          "word forms of Enlightenmentsuch asEnlightened"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A major milestone of the Age of Enlightenment was the 1751 publication by Denis Diderot [[deh-NEE dee-deh-ROH]] and Jean d'Alembert [[dah-lem-BEHR]] of what book, intended to be a \"systematic dictionary of the sciences, arts, and crafts\"? ANSWER:Encyclopédie(orEncyclopedia) 2021-22 C Set History (3) A Nazi operation named for this man included an order todefendBerlin\"tothelast bullet.\" This man, who may have coined the term \"ArmchairGeneral,\"assistedinorganizing theConventionofTauroggen[[toh-RAH-gen]]tocreateananti-Napoleoniccoalitionin1812. This man described the uncertainty of ongoing battles as the \"Fog of War\" and described warfare as a \"continuation of politics by other means.\" For ten points, name this nineteenth-century German military theorist who wroteOn War.",
        "answer": [
          "Carl vonClausewitz] or CarlPhilip Gottfried vonClausewitz BONUS: A predecessor to Clausewitz, Antoine-Henri Jomini ], wrote the book Summary of the Art of War and likely coined what term that describes maintaining an army's supply lines during conflict,",
          "more generally describes organizing an industry's supply chain? ANSWER:Logistics",
          "word forms such asLogistical"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Crippsmissionwasafailedattempttosecurethiscolony'sfullcooperationinits colonizer's World War Two efforts. This colony's Lucknow Pact united its rival Muslim League and a namesake National Congress. The last viceroy of this colony was Lord Mountbatten, who withheld support forthecreationofanindependentPakistan.Gainingits independence as the culmination ofthe3JunePlanwas,fortenpoints,whatsubcontinental British colony? ANSWER:India(accept the BritishRaj; accept DirectRule inIndia; accept Crown Rule in India; acceptIndian Empire; prompt on \"Bharata\") BONUS: This ally of Mahatma Gandhi and opponent of Muhammad Ali Jinnah was the first and longest-serving prime minister of independent India.",
        "answer": "JawaharlalNehru] 5 This mansupposedlycrossedachannelwhilewearingchainmailinataletoldbyhis rival, Unferth. A band of thanes who abandoned this king after encountering a dragon are later exiled by his successor, Wiglaf ]. This man tearsthearmsoffadescendant of Cain who terrorizes theHallofHeorot]ofKingHrothgar]. For ten points, name this hero of the Geats ] whodefeatsthemonsterGrendelina namesake epic poem. ANSWER:Beowulf"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Beowulf is written in what Middle Age language, virtually unreadable to contemporary speakers without study? ANSWER:Old English(acceptAnglo-Saxon; acceptEnglisc;prompt on \"English\") 2021-22 C Set History (6) In this state, former U.S. Army soldier Kevin Baugh [[BAW]] founded a 1.28 acre micronation knownastheRepublicofMolossia.ThediscoveryoftheComstockLodeledtoa mining boom around this state's Virginia City. As a response to the Great Depression, this statelegalized\"gaming\"inthe1930s.TheCarsonCityconventionledtothestatehoodof,for ten points, what western U.S. state? ANSWER:Nevada BONUS: The statehood of Nevada was rushedinanattempttoguaranteeAbrahamLincoln's victory over this Copperhead DemocratandformercommandinggeneraloftheU.S.Armyin the presidential election of 1864.",
        "answer": "George BrintonMcClellan"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Prohibition in the United States",
      "prompt": "Concerning the period of Prohibition in U.S. history, name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "\"Public Enemy Number One\" whose gang perpetrated the St. Valentine's Day Massacre.",
          "answer": "AlCaponeor Alphonse GabrielCapone"
        },
        {
          "question": "Nickname for Eliot Ness's \"incorruptible\" enforcers.",
          "answer": "TheUntouchables"
        },
        {
          "question": "Evangelist and former baseball player who claimed Prohibition would end all crime.",
          "answer": "BillySundayor Billy AshleySunday 2021-22 C Set History"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Prime Ministers of the United Kingdom",
      "prompt": "Concerning the British office of Prime Minister (PM), name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Conservative PM of the 1980s, dubbed \"The Iron Lady.\"",
          "answer": [
            "MargaretThatcheror Margaret HildaThatcher",
            "or BaronessThatcher"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Former mayor of London who led the UK during the COVID-19 pandemic.",
          "answer": "BorisJohnsonor Alexander Boris de PfeffelJohnson"
        },
        {
          "question": "PM who declared \"Peace in Our Time\" after appeasing Hitler.",
          "answer": "Arthur NevilleChamberlain"
        },
        {
          "question": "Son of an \"Elder\" PM who oversaw the end of the American Revolution.",
          "answer": "WilliamPittthe Younger"
        },
        {
          "question": "Liberal PM who gave the Midlothian Campaign speeches and opposed Disraeli.",
          "answer": "WilliamGladstoneor William Ewart Gladstone"
        },
        {
          "question": "De factofirst PM, in power during the beginningof the War of the Austrian Succession.",
          "answer": "RobertWalpole, 1st Earl of Orford"
        },
        {
          "question": "Conservative who signed the Good Friday Agreement and ratified the treaty to join the European Union.",
          "answer": "JohnMajor"
        },
        {
          "question": "Conservative successor of Churchill who resigned after bungling the Suez Crisis.",
          "answer": "AnthonyEden, 1st Earl of Avon or RobertAnthonyEden 2021-22 C Set History"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Banana Republics",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Author of \"The Gift of the Magi\" who coined the term \"Banana Republic.\"",
          "answer": "O.Henryor William SydneyPorter"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country whose Tegucigalpa-based government was overthrown on behalf of the Cuyamel [[KYE-ah-mel]] Fruit Company.",
          "answer": "Republic ofHondurasRepública deHonduras"
        },
        {
          "question": "Chilean poet and senator who criticized banana republics as exploitative in his book Canto General[[heh-neh-RAHL]].",
          "answer": "PabloNerudaor Ricardo Eliécer NeftalíReyesBasoalto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Guatemalan president who instituted anti-big business land reforms, leading to his overthrow by CIA-backed soldiers.",
          "answer": "JacoboÁrbenzJuan JacoboÁrbenzGuzmán 2021-22 C Set History"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A passage in thisbookisoftenconsideredthefirstpieceofpublicadvocacyfor a progressive tax. This book was written primarily to forge a new theory to replace the ideas of Mercantilists and Physiocrats. (20 pts)",
        "This book built upon its author's earlier TheoryofMoralSentimentsbylinkingtheconceptofthe\"InvisibleHand\" (10 pts)",
        "to production. For ten points, name this magnum opus of Scottish moral philosopher Adam Smith, considered a foundational text of classical economics. ANSWER:TheWealth of Nations(orAn Inquiry intothe Nature and Causes of theWealth of Nations) (2) Sebastian Sommer's hypothesis that buildings along this structure combined human barracks with horse stables was validated by excavations in the 2000s at South Shields. The Vallum (+) earthwork lay to the south of this structure, which added to pre-existing forts in a line from Solway Firth to the River Tyne. Picts and other Caledonian tribes lived north of this structure, which began constructionin(*) 122AD.Fortenpoints,namethis73-milebarrierthatformedthenorthernborderofRoman Britain. ANSWER:Hadrian's Wall(acceptVallum AeliumorVallumHadrianibefore \"Vallum\"; acceptPict's Wallbefore \"Picts\"; prompt on \"RomanWall\") (3) While campaigning inJuiz[[HWEZ]]deFora,thiscandidatewasstabbedbelow his bulletproof vest by a man who claimed to be\"onamissionfromGod.\"AFacebook group called \"Women Against\" [this politician] sparked the (+) Ele Não [[EH-lay \"NOW\"]] demonstration against his policies. This successor to Michel Temer [[TEM-ehr]] led the movement to remove left-leaning president Dilma Rousseff [[ROO-sef]] while serving as federal deputy of (*) Rio de Janeiro. For ten points, name this man who in 2019 became the president of Brazil."
      ],
      "answer": "JairBolsonaroor Jair MessiasBolsonaro"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Description Acceptable. A dispute over who accomplished this feat led to the SmithsonianwronglyattributingittoengineerSamuelLangley.Thisfeat,whichlasted 59 seconds, (20 pts)",
        "waslaunchedfromaninclineonKillDevilHill.Bicyclestoreemployee Charlie Taylor built a lightweight gasoline motor to make this feat possible for the vessel Flyer I. Kitty Hawk, (10 pts)",
        "North Carolina was the sight of, for ten points, what feat accomplished by the Wright Brothers?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "TheFirstmanned, poweredFlightby the WrightBrothers",
        "theFirst manned, poweredFlightat Kitty Hawk",
        "descriptiveanswers 2021-22 C Set History"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Flying in the \"Little Red Plane\" to this nation, Marmaduke Grove failed to overthrow the Ibáñez [[eeh-BAH-nyez]] regime in 1930. Grove and fellow Marxists formed this nation's Partido Socialista, which was overthrown in (20 pts)",
        "1973 after the seizure of Moneda [[moh-NEH-dah]] Palace. In this country, Salvador Allende [[ah-YEHN-deh]], was replaced by a U.S.-backed military junta [[HOON-tah]]. (10 pts)",
        "For ten points, name this Andean country led for nearly twenty years by the reactionary Augusto Pinochet [[pee-noh-SHEH]]."
      ],
      "answer": "Republic ofChileor República deChile"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This sport is depicted in a Francisco de Goya sketch showingthehistorical\"El Campeador\" El Cid performingitonhorseback.ThetreatiseDeathintheAfternoonby Ernest (20 pts)",
        "Hemingway recounts the traditions surrounding this sport, particularlyin Pamplona. Doctors developed a special type of surgery to deal with injuries given by (10 pts)",
        "horns to practitioners of this sport. For ten points,namethisbloodysportperformedin Spanish-speaking nations bymatadors. ANSWER:Bullfighting (acceptToreo; acceptCorrida) (7) In this presidential election year, the failure of the Republican candidate to visit California governor Hiram Johnson likely swung the election in the Democratic candidate's favor. The New York World wrongly reported that Charles (+) Evans Hughes won this election cycle. The incumbent in this election cycle used the slogan \"He Kept Us Out of the War\" in reference to U.S. neutrality during World War One. Woodrow Wilson won (*)reelection in, for ten points,which U.S. election year?"
      ],
      "answer": "Election of1916"
    }
  ]
}